my concern uh wanting to move towards
something which is a
more long-term strategy was that game a
was
simply our genetic code our uh
tribal nature manifesting itself and
that moving from that to
anything which isn't that would be such
a monumental task that it would require
us to go through a new evolution
yep yeah fortunately this evolution
actually happened about
150 000 to 1.5 million years ago okay
this is really good news because if that
hadn't happened i agree with you that
the likelihood that we'd be able to sort
of
undergo an evolution of that magnitude
in real time with
the hitting the fan is essentially
zero um
so this is what i mean when i say that
human beings are not the same as other
primates
meaningfully like significantly
something happened and we're obviously
witnessing the consequences of that but
we can actually identify it now and dial
it back
in so the story kind of goes like this
i'll try to keep it
compact because we don't have infinite
time um
if you take a look at other primates
close promising orangutans
guerrillas chimpanzees et cetera what
you notice in humans
and in fact in this case all social
mammals you notice that they all have
access to a particular kind of
hierarchical structure particularly
among males
we can call it dominance hierarchy this
phrase has gotten a lot of traction over
the past year because of
uh the other jordan um
so that's commonplace and we have that
so you might say
our natural need to compete with each
other
for a certain kind of scarcity and to
organize ourselves into
effective competing bands is real that's
a real part of our nature
but human beings also have and is the
thing that actually makes us human
and not other kinds of primates a
different
way of doing things it's called a
prestige
hierarchy which is odd because it's not
really a hierarchy but it's called a
prestige dynamic
so we've got the dominance dynamic which
is a hierarchy and the prestige dynamic
other primates don't have the prestige
dynamic
this is a incomprehensibly fundamental
thing so it's worth sort of actually
slowing down
chimpanzees do not do a very good job of
learning from each other
if a particular chimpanzee has
discovered something neato
it doesn't spread through the through
the band or the troop
this is because dominance hierarchies
are premised on mostly physical violence
so a dominant male
is able to beat the crap out of other
males and therefore establish himself as
dominant
and he may have a small number of beta
buddies who kind of like
get the table scraps and to support him
but the big thing there is the way that
the males relate to each other is
largely
aversion meaning you don't make eye
contact with the dominant male because
that means it's a threat he's gonna kick
your ass
what's really hard to learn
things from other people if you don't
make eye contact with them
right yep human beings
found themselves over what appears to
have been a pretty darn long
exploration in evolutionary space
finding a way
to take advantage of the capacity of
learning
so to interject there some of the
listeners that are familiar with
previous episodes will know william von
hippel who wrote
the social leap it was an explanation of
how we went from uh australopithecus
uh out onto the plains the development
of the throwing arm and
all of this sort of stuff and one of the
big um uh discoveries or one of the big
claims that he made was that the
anticipation of felt needs and
unwanted needs was a real a real key
element here so the fact that
chimpanzee creates a tool let's say
simple tool for
poking at something creating some food
whatever it might be
at the end of the day it can't
anticipate the fact that it needs it
again so it just throws it away
and then the next day it comes back it's
got to make the tool again
yep however what the uh one of the
the main archaeological finds which
identified this movement
towards being able to anticipate unfelt
needs
was that multiple tools were being found
in sites where human ancestors had been
so what that meant was that not only had
they made them once and then thrown them
away they'd made them and then taken
them with them the next day
so yeah that anticipation and also you
know communication if you can't
communicate
and especially if you can't make eye
contact but even if you you know you've
got no sophisticated language at all
you're totally right how does the the
collective consciousness grow it doesn't
it does it so there's a very
large number like 17 maybe more
distinct innovations that kind of
have you ever seen there's like a
japanese puzzle that has a bunch of
different pieces where
you have to be able to actually be able
to twist pull
and and slide all at once in a very
smooth relationship to get it to move
is this like the just the world's
hardest rubik's cube kind of
kind of and the note the thing is it's
interesting is that if you pull
it it binds on the twist if you if you
slide it binds on the pull right so
you have to actually get all so
evolution of homo sapien sapiens was
kind of like that like you had to get
you had to get grandmothers which is a
neat thing like grandmother's the notion
that females live long enough that
a mother has a daughter and is still
alive
long enough to actually co-parent her
daughter's
children is a big deal yep you had to
get
fatherhood like the notion that males
could have a
lived selection a fitness adaptation by
virtue of putting their energy
into attending to the well-being of
their actual biological children
isn't neat is an innovation you had to
have a
capacity to have
anticipated needs you had to have a
capacity to enter into a relationship
long enough that communication
had a place to emerge and then you had
to have the development of the
physiological and neurological capacity
to explore the space of potential
communication
right so all of these pieces
you have to have all of them and they
kind of like slide against each other
until it snaps
into this new thing